Finding Aid for Department of Classical Studies (University of Michigan) records, 1878-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Classical Studies (University of Michigan) records 1878-2007, 1950-2000
University of Michigan. Department of Classical Studies.
5 linear feet
87149 C26 2
The University of Michigan Department of Classical Studies traces its origin to the 1840s language offerings in Latin and Greek. The current department dates back to the 1946 when the separate Latin and Greek programs were merged and the curriculum broadened to feature more classical art and archaeology and classic civilization courses. Records reflect the department's administrative functions, as well as their extensive public programming through lecture series, symposia, and international projects. This collection primarily contains materials from after the reunification of Latin and Greek under Classical Studies although some 19th century material is present.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the department beginning in 1958 (donor no. 7104 ). A large transfer was received in 2007
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction
The study of ancient languages was first officially instated at the University in 1841 with Latin and Greek taught in one department. The Reverend Joseph Whiting was appointed the first Professor of Greek and Latin Languages in 1843. The mission of the department was articulated in 1852 by new professor of Latin James Robinson Boise: "The primary object of this department is to give the student a critical knowledge of the structure of the ancient languages themselves, of the principles of interpretation, and of those rhetorical principles which will enable a person to express himself in idiomatic and perspicuous English." The department split shortly after, forming the Department of Latin and the Department of Greek, chaired by Erastus Otis Haven (later president of the University) and Professor Boise, respectively. These two courses of study remained distinct until their re-merger in 1946, forming the Department of Classical Studies as it exists today.
In 1957 Gerald Else was appointed chairman of the department, and various curricular revisions took place. Graduate studies were updated and strengthened, and the Interdisciplinary Program in Classical Art and Archaeology (IPCAA) was founded. Through the 1970s further reassessments of the department's focus yielded the addition of courses on translation, as well as increasing the resources devoted to classical archaeology. In this area the department works in collaboration with the Kelsey Museum of Archaeology and the papyrology collection. Classical Studies also partners with the Department of History in the administration of the interdisciplinary program in Greek and Roman History.
The department has been particularly active in sponsoring lecture series. Several endowed lecture series are hallmarks of the department's university and national presence. The Thomas Jerome lecture series grew out of a bequest to the department made in 1919 by the estate of Thomas Spencer Jerome. Jerome was a graduate of the University of Michigan and had gone on to practice law in Detroit, and later to serve as a consular agent in Sorrento, Italy, where he became fascinated by classical history. The Jerome Lectureship Committee administered the selection of lecturers and subsequent publication of their talks. The administration of the Jerome Lectureship was transferred to the Department of Classical Studies in 1995.
The Department of Classical Studies records contain a wide range documentation of the administrative functions of various aspects of the department. The bulk of material is after the fusion of Greek and Latin into one department, dating after the mid-1940s and extending through the mid 1990s. These files document many different kinds of departmental activities including lectureships, curriculum reviews, symposia, and faculty affairs. It also includes documentation of programs in which the Department of Classical Studies participated, such as the Interdisciplinary Program in Classical Art and Archaeology, and the Great Books Program.
The records are divided into six series: Administrative Files, Department of Greek, Department of Latin, Events, Faculty Meeting Minutes, and Publications. Within these series are several sub-series, most notably the Jerome Lectureship Committee within the Events series.
Subjects:
Classical philology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Greek.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Latin.
- Administrative Files 1929-2001
  The Administrative Files, 1929-2001 is a scattering of topical files including information on departmental governance, departmental reviews, and material on the Interdisciplinary Program in Classical Art and Archaeology (IPCAA).
  - Arch of Trajan at Beneventum 1929 (Box 1)
  - Bailey, Shakleton 1967-2002 (Box 1)
  - Classical Studies Library 1938-2001 (Box 1)
  - Copley Fund Correspondence 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - Departmental Archives Project (includes oral history interview with Shakleton Bailey) 1996 (Box 1)
  - Departmental Governance
    - Chairman's Advisory Committee and Committee Assignments 1977-1987 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Departmental Chair 1974-2001 (Box 1)
  - Departmental History 1944-1976 (Box 1)
  - Departmental Surveys and Reviews
    - 1962 (Box 1)
    - 1974 (Box 1)
    - 1981-1985 (Box 1)
  - Distinguished University Professor Advisory Committee 1983-1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Earthwatch Expedition Briefing the Circus at Carthage 1983 (Box 1)
  - Excavation Committee 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Graduate Minority Recruitment 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Graduate Program 1954-1961 (Box 1)
  - Great Books Program Review 2004 (Box 1)
  - Hatcher Library Correspondence 1985-1992 (Box 1)
  - Interdisciplinary program in Classical Art and Archaeology (IPCAA)
    - Correspondence 1967-1994 (Box 1)
    - Program Review 1985 (Box 1)
    - Program Review 1987 (Box 1)
    - Program Revisions 1980-1994 (Box 1)
  - Knudsvig Memorial Fund 1998-2000 (Box 1)
  - LSA Correspondence 1982-1990
    - Incoming (Box 1)
    - Outgoing (Box 1)
  - Papyrology Collection 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Program Objectives 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Scott, Thomas (Novelists responses 1949-1950 about importance of Latin study) Letters Collection, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Shakelton Bailey, David (PR Restricted) (Box 1)
- Department of Greek 1872-1878, 1931-1959
  The Department of Greek, 1872-1878, 1931-1959 series contains 19th century correspondence of Martin D'Ooge and Elisha Jones, as well as later material relating to Warren E. Black from the period before the Department of Greek and the Department of Latin merged. These records represent part of the initial accession from the Department of Classical Studies.
  - Correspondence and Papers
    - Martin L. D'Ooge and Elisha Jones 1872-1878 (Box 1)
    - Warren E. Black 1931-1959 (Box 1)
- Department of Latin 1924-1939
  The Department of Latin, 1924-1939 series contains various discrete topical files from the period before the Department of Greek and the Department of Latin merged. Materials includes budgetary items and information of programs for Latin teachers. These records represent part of the initial accession from the Department of Classical Studies.
  - Budget 1924/1925-1938/1939 (Box 1)
  - Institute for Latin Teachers 1935 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Teaching Positions 1932-1938 (Box 1)
- Events 1945-2003
  The Events, 1945-2003 series, contains records created in the process of administering the wide range of public events and lecture programs sponsored by the Department of Classical Studies. Subseries reflect the different lectureship funds and include the Gerald Else Lectures, 1981, 1999-2002; the Jerome Lectureship, 1945-2003; and the Roger A. Pack Memorial Lectureship. Files typically include biographical information on the lecturers and any programs or publicity from their activities in Ann Arbor. These files directly reflect the department's system of tracking lecturers, and were often referred to in the course of planning and managing subsequent events.
  - General Colloquia, Lectures, Symposia
    - 1994-1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 2)
    - 2000 (Box 2)
    - 2001 (Box 2)
    - 2002, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 2003, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Gerald F. Else Lecture 1981, 1999-2002
    - Bernard Knox (1981) (Box 2)
    - Charles Segal (1999) (Box 2)
    - Bernd Seidensticker (2000) (Box 2)
    - Helene Foley (2001) (Box 2)
    - Daniel Mendelsohn (2002) (Box 2)
  - Jerome Lectureship Committee 1945-2003
    - Historical Files
      - Lectureship History (Box 2)
      - T.S. Jerome Archives (Box 2)
      - T.S. Jerome Biography (Box 2)
    - Administrative Files
      - Committee Membership (Box 2)
      - Move to Classics Dept. 1995 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence
      - 1945-1950 (Box 2)
      - 1951-1955 (Box 2)
      - 1956-1959 (Box 2)
      - 1960-1964 (Box 2)
      - 1965-1969 (Box 2)
      - 1970-1977 (Box 2)
      - 1986-1994 (Box 2)
    - Finances
      - 1950-1954 (Box 3)
      - 1955-1960 (Box 3)
      - 1960-1982 (Box 3)
      - 1984-1990 (Box 3)
      - 1990-1994 (Box 3)
      - 1998-2000 (Box 3)
      - 2001-2003 (Box 3)
    - Lecturers
      - Adcock, Sir Frank (1957) (Box 3)
      - Alföldi, Andrew (1961) (Box 3)
      - Boak, A.E.R. (Box 3)
      - Boëthius, Axel (Box 3)
      - Bowersock, Glen (1989) (Box 3)
      - Brown, Frank (1977) (Box 3)
      - Carter, Joseph (Box 3)
      - De Romilly, Jacqueline (Box 3)
      - Dinsmoor, William Bell (1956) (Box 3)
      - Gabba, Emilio (Box 3)
      - Grafton, Anthony (1992) (Box 3)
      - Hanfmann, George M.A. (1971) (Box 3)
      - Harrison, R. Martin (1990), 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Heisenberg, Werner (Box 3)
      - Hölscher, Tonio (Box 3)
      - Johnson, Allen C. (Box 3)
      - Krautheimer, Richard (1960) (Box 3)
      - Lavin, Irving (1985) (Box 3)
      - Millar, Fergus (Box 3)
      - Momigliano, Arnaldo D. (1972) (Box 3)
      - Nicolet, Claude (Box 3)
      - Pallottino, Massimo (1968) (Box 3)
      - Pelikan, Jaroslav (1996) (Box 4)
      - Purcell, Nicholas (Box 4)
      - Richter, Gisela (Box 4)
      - Ridgeway, Brunhilde (1981 1983) (Box 4)
      - Ridgeway, David (Box 4)
      - Sjöqvist, Erik (1967) (Box 4)
      - Taylor, Lily Ross (1965) (Box 4)
      - Torelli, Mario (1978) (includes photos) (Box 4)
      - Vermeule, Cornelius (1975) (Box 4)
      - Ward-Perkins, J.B. (1969) (Box 4)
      - Zanker, Paul (Box 4)
      - Rejections/Cancellations (Box 4)
      - Rome Symposium 1971 (Box 4)
    - Meeting Files
      - Rome November 16, 1966 (Box 4)
      - New York City January 13, 1973 (Box 4)
      - Ann Arbor December 12, 1974 (Box 4)
      - New York City January 9, 1975 (Box 4)
      - New York City December 27, 1976 (Box 4)
      - Ann Arbor January 12, 1978 (Box 4)
      - Ann Arbor October 17, 1978 (Box 4)
      - Rome June 20, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Rome January 21, 1982 (Box 4)
      - New York City December 1, 1983 (Box 4)
      - New York City January 5, 1987 (Box 4)
      - Rome May 23, 1988 (Box 4)
      - New York City January 24, 1990 (Box 4)
      - New Orleans, LA December 27, 1992 (Box 4)
      - New York City May 17, 1993 (Box 4)
      - Rome, Italy May 1996 (Box 4)
      - Chicago 1997 (Box 4)
    - Publications (Box 4)
    - Symposia
      - Rome Symposium 1971, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Seaborne Mediterranean Trade 1978 (Box 4)
  - Roger A. Pack Memorial Lecture
    - Donations 1994 (Box 4)
    - Michael Haslam Lecture (1994) (Box 4)
    - Pack's Death 1994 (Box 4)
- Faculty Meeting Minutes 1947-2003
  The Faculty Meeting Minutes, 1947-2003 series contains a complete run of minutes from faculty meetings from 1947-2003. Minutes often discuss curriculum issues, current department activities, and budgetary concerns.
  - 1947-1948 (Box 5)
  - 1949-1950 (Box 5)
  - 1951-1957 (Box 5)
  - 1958-1964 (Box 5)
  - 1965-1966 (Box 5)
  - 1967-1968 (Box 5)
  - 1969-1970 (Box 5)
  - 1971-1972 (Box 5)
  - 1974-1974 (Box 5)
  - 1974-1975 (Box 5)
  - 1975-1976 (Box 5)
  - 1976-1977 (Box 5)
  - 1977-1978 (Box 5)
  - 1978-1979 (Box 5)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 5)
  - 1981-1982 (Box 5)
  - 1982-1983 (Box 5)
  - 1983-1984 (Box 5)
  - 1984-1985 (Box 5)
  - 1985-1986 (Box 5)
  - 1986-1987 (Box 5)
  - 1987-1988 (Box 5)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - 1989-1990 (Box 5)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 5)
  - 1991-1992 (Box 5)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 5)
  - 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - 1995-1996 (Box 5)
  - 1996-1997 (Box 5)
  - 1997-1998 (Box 5)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 5)
  - 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - 2001-2002 (Box 5)
  - 2002-2003 (Box 5)
- Publications
  The Publications, 1931-2007 series includes materials that the department published for circulation. In this series is the departmental newsletter, and published materials from the department's summer programs.
  - Newsletter
    - The Classical Courier, 1942-1945 (Box 5)
    - The Classical Courier, 1946-1953 (Box 5)
    - The Michigan Classic, 1984-1987 (Box 5)
    - The Michigan Classic, 1988-1992 (Box 5)
    - Convivium, 2002-2004 (Box 5)
    - Convivium, 2005-2007 (Box 5)
  - Summer Programs
    - 1931-1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960-1972 (Box 5)